<Models><Model maker_group='Sabah' model_fil='danum-valley' model_type='c' model_group='danum'>Danum Valley Conservation Area<grv>www-adventures-danum-valley.jpg</grv><o>danum-valley</o><fimg>danum-valley-conservation-area.jpg</fimg><desc>If you are a wildlife and nature geek, you will find paradise in Danum Valley - a 472km sq conservation area of pristine, mostly primary, lowland dipterocarp forest that is home to 300 species of birds, mammals, insects etc. Sabah yesteryears` rampant jungle clearing left only a handful of forest untouched and Danum Valley Conservation Area is one of them. The area boasts an amazing...</desc><intro>-</intro></Model><Model maker_group='Sabah' model_fil='danum-valley' model_type='n' model_group='danum'>Borneo Rainforest Lodge<grv>-</grv><o>borneo-rainforest-lodge</o><fimg>borneo-rainforest-lodge.jpg</fimg><desc>With 5 star rating, Borneo Nature Lodge is tucked within the conservation area and is built to cater to tourist or wildlife and nature enthusiasts. Tastefully designed and built into its surrounding environment, BRL provides excellent service, food and accommodation.</desc><intro>-</intro></Model><Model maker_group='Sabah' model_fil='danum-valley,poiu' model_type='n' model_group='danum'>Danum Valley Field Center (5)<grv>www-adventures-danum-valley.jpg</grv><o>dvfc</o><fimg>danum-valley-conservation-area.jpg</fimg><desc>If you are a wildlife and nature geek, you will find paradise in Danum Valley - a 472km sq conservation area of pristine, mostly primary, lowland dipterocarp forest that is home to 300 species of birds, mammals, insects etc. Sabah yesteryears` rampant jungle clearing left only a handful of forest untouched and Danum Valley Conservation Area is one of them. The area boasts an amazing diversity of animal life including highly endangered species...</desc><intro>-</intro></Model><Model maker_group='Sabah' model_fil='dvfc' model_type='n' model_group='danum'>3D2N DVFC standard program<grv>www-adventures-danum-valley.jpg</grv><o>3d2n-dvfc</o><fimg>danum-valley-field-center.jpg</fimg><desc>The Danum Valley Field Center was established in 1986 as a center for conducting researches and supporting scientists in rainforest studies. Today, the center is one of the leading field centers of its kind in Southeast Asia, fully equipped with laboratory, conference room, scientist and research assistants living quarters, dorms, camping grounds, eating lounge, and internet facility.</desc><intro>-</intro></Model><Model maker_group='Sabah' model_fil='dvfc' model_type='n' model_group='danum'>4D3N DVFC standard program<grv>-</grv><o>4d3n-dvfc</o><fimg>danum-valley-field-center_.jpg</fimg><desc>The Danum Valley Field Center was established in 1986 as a center for conducting researches and supporting scientists in rainforest studies. Today, the center is one of the leading field centers of its kind in Southeast Asia, fully equipped with laboratory, conference room, scientist and research assistants living quarters, dorms, camping grounds, eating lounge, and internet facility.</desc><intro>-</intro></Model><Model maker_group='Sabah' model_fil='dvfc' model_type='n' model_group='danum'>4D3N Sg Purut<grv>-</grv><o>sungai-purut</o><fimg>sungai-purut.jpg</fimg><desc>For the more adventurous, take visiting Danum Valley a step further and enter the interior of the valley. There are satellite camps set up on a trail network that lets you explore deep into the conservation area...</desc><intro>-</intro></Model><Model maker_group='Sabah' model_fil='dvfc' model_type='n' model_group='danum'>5D4N Wild Jungle to Luxury<grv>-</grv><grp>danum-valley</grp><o>wild-jungles-to-luxury</o><fimg>danum-wild-jungles-to-luxury.jpg</fimg><desc>Wake up to the calls of gibbons and start your day with guided trek to interesting locations. Reward is high as you get to see pristine forest, wildlife, and beautiful waterfalls.</desc><intro>-</intro></Model> <Model maker_group='Sabah' model_fil='dvfc' model_type='n' model_group='danum'>7D6N Mt Danum Expedition<grv>-</grv><grp>danum-valley</grp><o>mt-danum</o><fimg>danum-expedition-to-mt-danum.jpg</fimg><desc>Experience amazing day on the mountain, get on with the expedition style adventure and explore deep into the conservation area, walking where few have walked before...</desc><intro>-</intro></Model><Model maker_group='Sabah' model_fil='kinabatangan' model_type='c' model_group='kinabatangan'>Kinabatangan Floodplain<grv>www-adventures-kinabatangan.jpg</grv><o>kinabatangan</o><fimg>kinabatangan-floodplain.jpg</fimg><desc>The Kinabatangan Floodplain is an exceptional area of Sabah, an area recognized for its natural beauty and role in supporting diverse life. Consisting of five distinct habitats - waterlogged and dry forests, saline and freshwater swamps and limestone habitats - the lower Kinabatangan has one of the most diverse concentrations of wildlife in Borneo...</desc><intro>The Kinabatangan Floodplain is an exceptional area of Sabah, an area recognized for its natural beauty and role in supporting diverse life. Consisting of five distinct habitats - waterlogged and dry forests, saline and freshwater swamps and limestone habitats - the lower Kinabatangan has one of the most diverse concentrations of wildlife in Borneo. Expect to see Proboscis monkeys, hornbills, crocodiles, kingfishers, langurs, gibbons and various species of birds. Pygmy elephant and orang utans in the wild are also common. A visit to the river offers dusk and dawn boat cruises along the river, light trekking and night walks, and usually a visit to forest restoration areas managed by local communities, tour operators or conservation agencies.	brbrbrbr	We promote community tourism initiatives in form of homestays and jungle camps to offer unique experiences to adventurous travelers. These are located in less visited areas of the Kinabatangan. If these do not tickle your fancy, there are lodges with added comfort and luxury in the more visited villages of Sukau and Bilit.</intro></Model><Model maker_group='Sabah' model_fil='kinabatangan' model_type='n' model_group='kinabatangan'>3D2N Abai Homestay<grv>-</grv><o>abai-homestay</o><fimg>abai-village-homestay.jpg</fimg><desc>One of the most picturesque villages on the Kinabatangan, Abai village is located closest to the river mouth that pours itself out onto the Sulu Sea. Reachable only by a 2 hour boat ride from Sandakan pier (60km)</desc><intro>-</intro></Model><Model maker_group='Sabah' model_fil='kinabatangan' model_type='n' model_group='kinabatangan'>3D2N Eco Camp<grv>-</grv><o>ecocamp-kinabatangan</o><fimg>eco-camp.jpg</fimg><desc>Trade the usual lodge experience with something more rustic - sleep in elevated A-framed huts under a mosquito net and wake up to a cacophony of birdsongs in the morning.</desc><intro>-</intro></Model><Model maker_group='Sabah' model_fil='kinabatangan' model_type='n' model_group='kinabatangan'>3D2N Supu Camp<grv>-</grv><o>supu-camp-kinabatangan</o><fimg>supu-camp.jpg</fimg><desc>Escape the tourist trail of Kinabatangan Floodplain by going to Supu. The Supu area promises added adventure aside from river cruises - sleep on a stretcher hammock in a forest camp perched high on the riverbank.</desc><intro>-</intro></Model><Model maker_group='Sabah' model_fil='kinabatangan' model_type='n' model_group='kinabatangan'>4D3N Homestay &amp; Supu Camp<grv>-</grv><o>homestay-supu-camp</o><fimg>homestay-and-supu-camp.jpg</fimg><desc>Escape the tourist trail of Kinabatangan Floodplain by going to Supu. The Supu area promises added adventure aside from river cruises - sleep on a stretcher hammock in a forest camp perched high on the riverbank.</desc><intro>-</intro></Model><Model maker_group='Sabah' model_fil='kinabatangan,resort' model_type='n' model_group='kinabatangan'>3D2N Borneo Nature Lodge<grv>-</grv><o>borneo-nature-lodge</o><fimg>borneo-nature-lodge.jpg</fimg><desc>Immerse yourself in nature's best, without having to compromise the rest. Borneo Nature Lodge strives to be an eco-friendly resort without having to compromise the green or your comfort.</desc><intro>-</intro></Model><Model maker_group='Sabah' model_fil='kinabatangan,resort' model_type='n' model_group='kinabatangan'>3D2N Kinabatangan Wetlands Resort<grv>-</grv><o>wetlands-resort</o><fimg>wetlands-resort.jpg</fimg><desc>Kinabatangan Wetlands Resort is a new gem located in Abai, a quieter area of the Lower Kinabatangan Floodplain, about 40km or about an hour`s boat ride from Sandakan harbor. If you are looking to get away...</desc><intro>-</intro></Model><Model maker_group='Sabah' model_fil='tabin' model_type='c' model_group='tabin'>Tabin Wildlife Reserve<grv>www-adventures-tabin.jpg</grv><o>tabin</o><fimg>tabin-wildlife-reserve.jpg</fimg><desc>Go off the grid for a few days at Tabin Wildlife Reserve, a nature preserve created in 1984 to preserve Sabah`s disappearing wild animals. Occupying a large part of the peninsula forming the northern headland of Darvel Bay.</desc><intro>-</intro></Model><Model maker_group='Sabah' model_fil='tabin' model_type='n' model_group='tabin'>3D2N Tabin Safari<grv>-</grv><o>tabin-wildlife-reserve</o><fimg>tabin-wildlife-reserve.jpg</fimg><desc>Go off the grid for a few days at Tabin Wildlife Reserve, a nature preserve created in 1984 to preserve Sabah's disappearing wild animals. Occupying a large part of the peninsula forming the northern headland of Darvel Bay.</desc><intro>-</intro></Model><Model maker_group='Sabah' model_fil='maliau-basin' model_type='c' model_group='maliau'>Maliau Basin Conservation Area<grv>www-adventures-maliau-basin.jpg</grv><o>maliau-basin</o><fimg>maliau-basin.jpg</fimg><desc>Often termed, "Sabah\'s Lost World", a reference to Sir Arthur Conan Doyle\'s mysterious land of immense, vine-clad jungles, majestic, towering, ancient trees, strange and rare wildlife - as well as a resident population of giant dinosaurs.</desc><intro>-</intro></Model><Model maker_group='Sabah' model_fil='maliau-basin' model_type='n' model_group='maliau'>4D3N Maliau Explorer<grv>-</grv><o>4d3n-maliau</o><fimg>maliau-basin_.jpg</fimg><desc>Often termed, "Sabah\'s Lost World", a reference to Sir Arthur Conan Doyle\'s mysterious land of immense, vine-clad jungles, majestic, towering, ancient trees, strange and rare wildlife - as well as a resident population of giant dinosaurs.</desc><intro>-</intro></Model><Model maker_group='Sabah' model_fil='maliau-basin' model_type='n' model_group='maliau'>5D4N Maliau Explorer<grv>-</grv><o>5d4n-maliau</o><fimg>maliau-basin.jpg</fimg><desc>Often termed, "Sabah\'s Lost World", a reference to Sir Arthur Conan Doyle\'s mysterious land of immense, vine-clad jungles, majestic, towering, ancient trees, strange and rare wildlife - as well as a resident population of giant dinosaurs.</desc><intro>-</intro></Model><Model maker_group='Sabah' model_fil='semporna-archipelago' model_type='c' model_group='semporna'>Semporna Archipelago<grv>www-adventures-semporna-archipelago.jpg</grv><o>semporna-archipelago</o><fimg>semporna-archipelago.jpg</fimg><desc>A trip to Mataking Island, a private island on the Celebes Sea is like a dream come true. While a lot of the other resorts in the archipelago caters mostly to the diver scene, at Reef Dive Resort you wiIl find that diver or not, there is a place for you here.</desc><intro>-</intro></Model><Model maker_group='Sabah' model_fil='semporna-archipelago,resort' model_type='n' model_group='semporna'>Reef Dive Resort<grv>-</grv><o>mataking-resort</o><fimg>mataking-island-resort.jpg</fimg><desc>A trip to Mataking Island, a private island on the Celebes Sea is like a dream come true. While a lot of the other resorts in the archipelago caters mostly to the diver scene...</desc><intro>-</intro></Model><Model maker_group='Sabah' model_fil='semporna-archipelago' model_type='n' model_group='semporna'>Seaventures Dive Rig<grv>-</grv><o>seaventures-dive-rig</o><fimg>seaventures-rig-resort.jpg</fimg><desc>Yes, it is an oil rig! What was once an exploration jack up rig is now an impressive rig resort. If your main draw to this area is diving, we highly recommend Seaventures.</desc><intro>-</intro></Model><Model maker_group='Sabah' model_fil='crocker-range' model_type='c' model_group='crocker'>Crocker Range National Park<grv>www-adventures-gunung-alab-hike.jpg</grv><o>crocker-range</o><fimg>gunung-alab.jpg</fimg><desc>The Crocker National Park covers 1,400 sq kilometers, and is home to at least 5 species of primates. With an abundance of birds, orchids, and nepenthes you will be rewarded with beautiful views...</desc><intro>-</intro></Model><Model maker_group='Sabah' model_fil='crocker-range' model_type='n' model_group='crocker'>2D1N Gunung Alab Hike<grv>-</grv><o>gunung-alab-hike</o><fimg>gunung-alab.jpg</fimg><desc>Located in the center of the Crocker Range, Gunung Alab is the perfect place for an adventurous 2 day trek through beautiful montane forest. The Crocker National Park covers 1,400 sq kilometers, and is home to at least 5 species of primates. With an abundance of birds, orchids, and nepenthes.</desc><intro>-</intro></Model><Model maker_group='Sabah' model_fil='crocker-range' model_type='n' model_group='crocker'>4D3N Trusmadi Trek<grv>-</grv><o>mt-trus-madi</o><fimg>mt-trus-madi.jpg</fimg><desc>Mt. Trus Madi is Sabah\'s 2nd highest peak, and located in the central part of Sabah. The Crocker National Park covers 1,400 sq kilometers, and is home to at least 5 species of primates. With an abundance of birds, orchids, and nepenthes you will be rewarded with beautiful views...</desc><intro>-</intro></Model><Model maker_group='Sabah' model_fil='sandakan' model_type='c' model_group='sandakan'>Sandakan &amp; Sepilok Area<grv>www-adventures-libaran-turtle-island-camping.jpg</grv><o>sandakan</o><fimg>libaran-turtle-island-camping.jpg</fimg><desc>It`s not camping, its glamping! Take on the outdoors in style and comfort, as Walai Penyu Libaran Resort offers a camp trip unlike any other. An establishment aimed at turtle conservation and awareness, Libaran Island Resort is located...</desc><intro>-</intro></Model><Model maker_group='Sabah' model_fil='sandakan,camping' model_type='n' model_group='sandakan'>2D1N Libaran Turtle Island Camping<grv>-</grv><o>libaran-turtle-island-camping</o><fimg>libaran-turtle-island-camping.jpg</fimg><desc>It`s not camping, its glamping! Take on the outdoors in style and comfort, as Walai Penyu Libaran Resort offers a camp trip unlike any other. An establishment aimed at turtle conservation and awareness, Libaran Island Resort is located...</desc><intro>-</intro></Model><Model maker_group='Sabah' model_fil='sandakan,resort' model_type='n' model_group='sandakan'>Lankayan Island Resort<grv>-</grv><o>lankayan</o><fimg>lankayan-island-resort.jpg</fimg><desc>Lankayan is a small tropical island in the Sulu Sea, about 90 minutes by boat from the port of Sandakan, and sits within a large Marine Protected Area with excellent diving. Unpopulated and circled by white sandy shore...</desc><intro>-</intro></Model><Model maker_group='Sabah' model_fil='mount-kinabalu' model_type='c' model_group='knpa' model_link='mount-kinabalu' model_img='' model_desc=''>Kinabalu National Park Area<grv>www-adventures-mt-kinabalu.jpg</grv><o>mount-kinabalu</o><fimg>mount-kinabalu.jpg</fimg><desc>It is the heart and soul of Sabah - ultimate pride of its people. Majestic Mount Kinabalu - the mountain and its surroundings are among the most important biological sites in the world.</desc><intro>-</intro></Model><Model maker_group='Sabah' model_fil='mount-kinabalu' model_type='n' model_group='knpa'>2D1N Mt Kinabalu Climb Standard<grv>-</grv><o>mount-kinabalu-climb</o><fimg>mount-kinabalu-basic-climb.jpg</fimg><desc>It is the heart and soul of Sabah - ultimate pride of its people. Majestic Mount Kinabalu - the mountain and its surroundings are among the most important biological sites in the world.</desc><intro>-</intro></Model><Model maker_group='Sabah' model_fil='mount-kinabalu' model_type='n' model_group='knpa'>2D1N Mt Kinabalu Climb Walk the Torq (with via ferrata)<grv>-</grv><o>mountain-torq-ferrata</o><fimg>mount-kinabalu-via-ferrata.jpg</fimg><desc>Want an added edge to your Mount Kinabalu climbing experience? Sign up for The Mountain Torq Via Ferrata, a mountain 'trail' made up of iron rungs, palettes (footholds), cables and rails.</desc><intro>-</intro></Model><Model maker_group='Sabah' model_fil='mount-kinabalu' model_type='n' model_group='knpa'>2D1N Mt Kinabalu Climb Low's Peak Circuit (with via ferrata)<grv>-</grv><o>lows-peak-circuit</o><fimg>mount-kinabalu-basic-climb.jpg</fimg><desc>Want an added edge to your Mount Kinabalu climbing experience? Sign up for The Low's Peak Circuit Via Ferrata, a mountain \'trail\' made up of iron rungs, palettes (footholds), cables and rails.</desc><intro>-</intro></Model><Model maker_group='Sabah' model_fil='mount-kinabalu,camping' model_type='n' model_group='knpa'>3D2N Mt Kinabalu Camping<grv>-</grv><o>mt-kinabalu-camping</o><fimg>mount-kinabalu-camping.jpg</fimg><desc>Sayap Substation is a little used entrance to Kinabalu National Park with vast jungle, a temperate climate, and an abundance of biodiversity. Located at 1,080 meters above sea level, the primary rainforest is filled with orchids, giant trees and waterfalls.</desc><intro>-</intro></Model><Model maker_group='Sabah' model_fil='mount-kinabalu' model_type='n' model_group='knpa'>3D2N Tambatuon Village Experience<grv>-</grv><o>kampung-tambatuon</o><fimg>tambatuon-village.jpg</fimg><desc>The perfect setting for rest and relaxation, Tambatuon is located on the foothills of Mount Kinabalu, in a beautiful valley by the Kedamaian River. Paddy fields and fruit orchards aplenty, discover the amazing hospitality of the Dusun tribe.</desc><intro>-</intro></Model><Model maker_group='Sabah' model_fil='orou-sapulot' model_type='c' model_group='orou'>Orou Sapulot-Murut Country Adventure<grv>www-adventures-orou-sapulot.jpg</grv><o>orou-sapulot</o><fimg>sapulot-country-adventure.jpg</fimg><desc>Venturing into the lesser-known Sapulot country means encountering Murut hospitality; drink bottomless rice wine from huge ceramic jars and chat about their headhunting ancestors.</desc><intro>-</intro></Model><Model maker_group='Sabah' model_fil='orou-sapulot' model_type='n' model_group='orou'>3D2N Sapulot<grv>-</grv><grp>orou-sapulot</grp><o>3d2n-sapulot</o><fimg>sapulot-country-adventure.jpg</fimg><desc>Venturing into the lesser-known Sapulot country means encountering Murut hospitality; drink bottomless rice wine from huge ceramic jars and chat about their headhunting ancestors.</desc><intro>-</intro></Model><Model maker_group='Sabah' model_fil='orou-sapulot' model_type='n' model_group='orou'>4D3N Sapulot<grv>-</grv><o>4d3n-sapulot</o><fimg>sapulot-country-adventure_.jpg</fimg><desc>Venturing into the lesser-known Sapulot country means encountering Murut hospitality; drink bottomless rice wine from huge ceramic jars and chat about their headhunting ancestors.</desc><intro>-</intro></Model><Model maker_group='Sabah' model_fil='day-trips-sabah' model_type='c' model_group='daytrips'>Sabah Daytrips<grv>www-adventures-tunku-abdul-rahman-park-under-water.jpg</grv><o>day-trips-sabah</o><fimg>diving-tunku-abdul-rahman-park.jpg</fimg><desc>It's so easy to hit the road for day trips. There are so many fun ways to explore the streets, neighbourhoods and attractions of Borneo in a short period of time. Day trip or daycation can be a very popular form of recreation and leisure for travelers. Find out what we can offer for your day trip adventures.</desc><intro>-</intro></Model><Model maker_group='Sabah' model_fil='day-trips-sabah' model_type='n' model_group='daytrips'>Sea Kayaking Halfday / Fullday<grv>-</grv><o>sea-kayaking-kota-kinabalu</o><fimg>sea-kayaking.jpg</fimg><desc>The Tunku Abdul Rahman Marine Park boasts several islands just minutes from Kota Kinabalu city. Well-known for its beaches, snorkeling and diving, would it not be fun to kayak out there from the beach on the mainland?</desc><intro>-</intro></Model><Model maker_group='Sabah' model_fil='day-trips-sabah' model_type='n' model_group='daytrips'>Stand­up Paddleboarding<grv>-</grv><o>stand-up-paddle-boarding</o><fimg>stand-up-paddle-boarding.jpg</fimg><desc>Find peace, balance and tranquility on the often flocked Sapi Island with the help of a paddle and a board. Taking you above and below the turquoise waters, paddle away from the rippling shores of Sapi Island in search of hidden sights and snorkeling grounds.</desc><intro>-</intro></Model><Model maker_group='Sabah' model_fil='day-trips-sabah' model_type='n' model_group='daytrips'>Whitewater Rafting - Kiulu/Padas<grv>-</grv><grp>day-trips-sabah</grp><o>water-rafting</o><fimg>water-rafting.jpg</fimg><desc>A full day of adventure awaits when you decide to raft the Kiulu/Padas River!</desc><intro>-</intro></Model><Model maker_group='Sabah' model_fil='day-trips-sabah' model_type='n' model_group='daytrips'>Tunku Abdul Rahman Park Diving or Snorkel<grv>-</grv><o>tunku-abdul-rahman-park</o><fimg>diving-tunku-abdul-rahman-park.jpg</fimg><desc>The Tunku Abdul Rahman Park (TARP) is the underwater playground of Kota Kinabalu. Situated in the South China Sea, TARP is located only a short boat ride away from this vibrant city's waterfront.</desc><intro>-</intro></Model><Model maker_group='Sabah' model_fil='day-trips-sabah,cooking' model_type='n' model_group='daytrips'>Momma's House Cooking Class<grv>-</grv><o>mh-cooking-class</o><fimg>mh-cooking-class.jpg</fimg><desc>Get outside the city and into the kitchen with our specialty outdoor cooking classes, located at "Momma\'s House" about 15 minutes outside of kota kinabalu.</desc><intro>-</intro></Model><Model maker_group='Sabah' model_fil='kudat' model_type='c' model_group='kudat'>Kudat<grv>www-adventures-hibiscus-villa.jpg</grv><o>kudat</o><fimg>kudat.jpg</fimg><desc>Beach getaway to relax with family and friends for a few days.</desc><intro>-</intro></Model><Model maker_group='Sabah' model_fil='kudat' model_type='n' model_group='kudat'>Hibiscus Villa<grv>-</grv><o>hibiscus-villa</o><fimg>hibiscus-villa.jpg</fimg><desc>If you are looking for an idyllic beach getaway to relax with family and friends for a few days without sacrificing comfort and luxury, and wanting to get away from the big resorts, Hibiscus Villa is the place for you.</desc><intro>-</intro></Model><Model maker_group='Sabah' model_fil='kudat' model_type='n' model_group='kudat'>Hibiscus Beach Retreat<grv>-</grv><o>hibiscus-beach-retreat</o><fimg>hibiscus-beach-retreat.jpg</fimg><desc>A sister lodge to Hibiscus Villa, the Hibiscus Beach Retreat is a self-contained one-bedroom chalet right on the beach, perfect for couples and small families looking for privacy at an absolutely...</desc><intro>-</intro></Model><Model maker_group='Sabah' model_fil='kota-belud' model_type='c' model_group='kb'>Kota Belud<trv>Kota Belud</trv><grv>www-adventures-manana-borneo_.jpg</grv><o>kota-belud</o><fimg>kota-belud.jpg</fimg><desc>If you are looking for a no-frills beach getaway in a secluded location, away from the maddening crowd of the marine park of Kota Kinabalu, look no further than Kota Belud.</desc><intro>-</intro></Model><Model maker_group='Sabah' model_fil='kota-belud' model_type='n' model_group='kb'>Manana Borneo<grv>-</grv><o>manana-borneo</o><fimg>manana-borneo.jpg</fimg><desc>If you are looking for a no-frills beach getaway in a secluded location, away from the maddening crowd of the marine park of Kota Kinabalu, look no further than Manana Borneo.</desc><intro>-</intro></Model><Model maker_group='Sarawak' model_fil='bako-national-park' model_type='c' model_group='bnp'>Bako National Park<grv>www-adventures-bako.jpg</grv><o>bako-national-park</o><fimg>bako.jpg</fimg><desc>Bako is one of the best national parks in Malaysia to see wildlife in a natural setting and experience the rainforest via a network of trekking trails.</desc><intro>-</intro></Model><Model maker_group='Sarawak' model_fil='bako-national-park' model_type='n' model_group='bnp'>2D1N Bako<grv>-</grv><o>bako</o><fimg>bako.jpg</fimg><desc>Bako is one of the best national parks in Malaysia to see wildlife in a natural setting and experience the rainforest via a network of trekking trails.</desc><intro>-</intro></Model><Model maker_group='Sarawak' model_fil='ulu-ai' model_type='c' model_group='ua'>Ulu Ai Experiences<grv>www-adventures-ulu-ai.jpg</grv><o>ulu-ai</o><fimg>lubuk-kasai-jungle.jpg</fimg><desc>A visit to a longhouse is often the highlight of a trip to Sarawak, offering a glimpse into the lifestyle of the various tribes who have for generations lived in the remote interior of Borneo.</desc><intro>bbbbNanga Sumpa programsqqqq	brbrA visit to a longhouse is often the highlight of a trip to Sarawak, offering a glimpse into the lifestyle of the various tribes who have for generations lived in the remote interior of Borneo. While there are many areas in Sarawak where longhouses can be visited, Ulu Ai is one of the best. What makes Ulu Ai so special is the natural environment and stunning scenery. Clean rivers and jungle streams, refreshing waterfalls and undisturbed tracts of rainforest allow you to combine a range of outdoor activities with a longhouse visit.	brbrbrbrLocated on the banks of the Delok River, approximately a 1½ hour longboat ride from the Batang Ai Lake. This award-winning operation was established in 1987 in partnership between the people of Nanga Sumpa longhouse and a local tour operator. The lodge currently consists of an older main building containing the dining area, kitchen and staff rooms plus two new accommodation wings built in 2014.	brbrbrbrThe three new Forest Rooms at Nanga Sumpa are approximately 35 m2 in size and include ensuite bathrooms. The rooms have mesh on the windows to keep insects out. The three rooms share an Iban-style ruai, or covered verandah. Each of the Forest Rooms can comfortably accommodate four people. These spacious rooms are ideal for families or couples seeking a higher level of comfort and privacy than was previously offered at Nanga Sumpa Lodge.	brbrbrbrThe new Ruai wing offers rooms with shared bathroom facilities. The building has five guest rooms, a multi-use space and its own shower and toilet block. The Ruai is linked to the new Forest Rooms and the main lodge building by a wooden walkway.	brbrbrbrA generator supplies electricity from 6.30-10.30 pm to power the main lights and fans. Solar powered nightlights illuminate the public areas, walkways and bathrooms. Meals are prepared in the lodge and feature rice, noodles, chicken, fish, fresh jungle vegetables and other local delicacies.</intro></Model><Model maker_group='Sarawak' model_fil='ulu-ai' model_type='n' model_group='ua'>3D2N Nanga Sumpa<grv>-</grv><o>nanga-sumpa</o><fimg>nanga-sumpa.jpg</fimg><desc>Nanga Sumpa is a jungle lodge located in a relatively remote area of Borneo. The facilities reflect the remote location and are somewhat basic, and accommodation may not be as luxurious as some travellers require.</desc><intro>-</intro></Model><Model maker_group='Sarawak' model_fil='ulu-ai' model_type='n' model_group='ua'>3D2N Nanga Sumpa &amp; Lubok Kasai<grv>-</grv><o>nanga-sumpa-lubuk-kasai</o><fimg>nanga-sumpa-lubuk-kasai.jpg</fimg><desc>This program combines the Nanga Sumpa Longhouse &amp; Lubok Kasai Jungle Camp experience; the Lubok Kasai Camp is located a 30-45 minute boat ride upriver from Nanga Sumpa, deep in the heart of Borneo. It is situated on the banks of the Lalang River in an area where orangutan are sighted.</desc><intro>-</intro></Model><Model maker_group='Sarawak' model_fil='ulu-ai' model_type='n' model_group='ua'>4D3N Lubok Kasai Jungle Experience<grv>-</grv><o>lubuk-kasai-jungle</o><fimg>lubuk-kasai-jungle.jpg</fimg><desc>Meet the Iban people, enjoy the pleasures of upriver travel, stay at the Lubok Kasai jungle camp &amp; experience the Borneo rainforest on this program. The Lubok Kasai Camp is located a 30-45 minute boat ride upriver from Nanga Sumpa, deep in the heart of Borneo. It is situated on the...</desc><intro>-</intro></Model><Model maker_group='Sarawak' model_fil='ulu-ai' model_type='n' model_group='ua'>4D3N Longhouse to Longhouse Trek<grv>-</grv><o>longhouse-trek</o><fimg>longhouse-trek.jpg</fimg><desc>This trek gives you the opportunity to see not only one Iban community but two; both settlement located on the edge of the forest in beautiful settings, and offer a great opportunity to experience and understand Iban life.</desc><intro>-</intro></Model><Model maker_group='Sarawak' model_fil='ulu-ai' model_type='n' model_group='ua'>5D4N Red Ape Trail<grv>-</grv><o>redape-trail</o><fimg>redape-trail.jpg</fimg><desc>Dedicated to true trekkers, The Red Ape Trail is a challenging but rewarding 3 full day trek that passes through orangutan habitat deep in the heart of the Sarawak rainforest.</desc><intro>-</intro></Model><Model maker_group='Sarawak' model_fil='mulu-national-park' model_type='c' model_group='mnp'>Mulu National Park<grv>www-adventures-mulu-showcaves.jpg</grv><o>mulu-national-park</o><fimg>mulu-showcaves.jpg</fimg><desc>Gunung Mulu National Park is one of nature’s most astounding features in Sarawak\'s expanding network of national parks. It is also the largest national park, covering 544 sq km of primary rainforest...</desc><intro>-</intro></Model><Model maker_group='Sarawak' model_fil='mulu-national-park' model_type='n' model_group='mnp'>3D2N Mulu Showcaves<grv>-</grv><o>mulu-showcaves</o><fimg>mulu-showcaves.jpg</fimg><desc>Gunung Mulu National Park is one of nature’s most astounding features in Sarawak\'s expanding network of national parks. It is also the largest national park, covering 544 sq km of primary rainforest...</desc><intro>-</intro></Model><Model maker_group='Sarawak' model_fil='mulu-national-park' model_type='n' model_group='mnp'>4D3N Mulu Showcaves &amp; Pinnacles<grv>-</grv><o>mulu-showcaves-and-pinnacles</o><fimg>mulu-showcaves-pinnacles.jpg</fimg><desc>Combining the Showcaves with Pinnacles, this is an adventure-packed trip. The famous Pinnacles at Mulu consists of a series of 45metre high, razor-sharp limestone spikes that tower above the surrounding...</desc><intro>-</intro></Model><Model maker_group='Sarawak' model_fil='mulu-national-park' model_type='n' model_group='mnp'>5D4N Headhunter\'s Trail<grv>-</grv><o>headhunter-trail</o><fimg>headhunter-trail.jpg</fimg><desc>Discover the show caves of Mulu National Park, climb the Pinnacles and trek the headhunters\' trail on a 5 days/4 nights tour of the Mulu's UNESCO World Heritage Site.</desc><intro>-</intro></Model><Model maker_group='Sarawak' model_fil='day-trips-sarawak' model_type='c' model_group='daytrips-sarawak'>Sarawak Daytrips<grv>www-adventures-rainforest-kayaking.jpg</grv><o>day-trips-sarawak</o><fimg>rainforest-kayaking-adventure.jpg</fimg><desc>It's so easy to hit the road for day trips. There are so many fun ways to explore the streets, neighbourhoods and attractions of Borneo in a short period of time. Day trip or daycation can be a very popular form of recreation and leisure for travelers. Find out what we can offer for your day trip adventures.</desc><intro>-</intro></Model><Model maker_group='Sarawak' model_fil='day-trips-sarawak' model_type='n' model_group='daytrips-sarawak'>Santubong Wildlife Cruise<grv>-</grv><o>santubong-wildlife-cruise</o><fimg>santubong.jpg</fimg><desc>Cruise the rivers and mangroves of Santubong and go in search of Irrawaddy dolphins, proboscis monkeys, crocodiles and other wildlife.</desc><intro>-</intro></Model><Model maker_group='Sarawak' model_fil='day-trips-sarawak' model_type='n' model_group='daytrips-sarawak'>Rainforest Kayaking Adventure<grv>-</grv><o>rainforest-kayaking-adventure</o><fimg>rainforest-kayaking-adventure.jpg</fimg><desc>Let\'s get back to basic! The Bamboo Rafting adventure program offers a unique and memorable experience with traditional raft along the beautiful river.</desc><intro>-</intro></Model></Models>